Louis J. Budd Papers and compilation of Mark Twain Resources, 1980-2008, undated
Elmira College
- SERIES 3: MARK TWAIN INTERVIEWS, undated; This series compiled by Louis J. Budd contains photocopies and transcriptions of Mark Twain interviews. Dates reflect the date of the original article and not the date of reproduction. This series contains Budd’s original folder headings and is arranged ch
  - New York World -- "My Impressions of America/And Kate Carew's Impressions of the Great Humorist/An Interview in Which He Refuses to Be Interviewed/Eluding the Subject Proposed, He Talks About Almost Everything Else, Including Truth, Waiters, Early breakfasts, Wisdom and Noise" -- Clemens was submitting to being sketched rather than interviewed and said little of consequence", October 21, 1900
  - New York World -- "Wouldn't Work 30 Minutes for 500 Dollars/Declares That He Only Does Work When It Is an Absolute Necessity" -- "Clemens declines to cover a Bryan mass meeting for the WORLD", October 21, 1900
  - Hartford Current -- "What Mr. Clemens Said/His Grief at News of Mr. Warner's Death/Old Days Recalled/Humorist's Plans" -- "Clemens also praises Plasmon and asks about Connecticut politics", October 26, 1900
  - New York Journal and Advertiser -- "A Day with Mark Twain/Funniest Man in the World/Pictorially Told by Vivid Snap Shots at America's Famous Humorist" -- "Clemens explains why he has decided to shun serious interviews; comments on unrelated matters, with most about his visit to the jail in Pretoria (possibly a pastiche of other interviews)", November 11, 1900
  - New York World -- "Sure Mark Twain is in a Crooked Game/Housekeeper who did No. 14 East on Tenth Street Annoyed by Inquiries for Him/He's at No. 14 West" -- "Clemens, while commenting on a housekeeper who did not recognize either of his names, insists that he cannot afford to talk to the press free of charge", November 12, 1900
  - New York World -- "Mark Twain at Football Game" -- "Clemens attends Yale-Princeton game and makes a few spectator's remarks", November 18, 1900
  - New York Times Sun, Tribune, World -- "Mark Twain is Avenged/One False/Cabby Learns the Power of His Wrath" -- "Not an interview but a long and interesting report of Clemens appearing in magistrate's court in New York City to press a complaint against a cabman who had overcharged his housekeeper", November 23, 1900
  - New York Herald -- "Mark Twain in His New York Den" -- "A combination feature-story interview, with many photographs; Clemens comments mostly on persons appealing for money criticizes grand opera", January 20, 1901
  - New York Times -- "Mark Twain Hazing/Calls West Point Cadets Who Indulge in It Cowards" -- "Clemens speaks out briefly against hazing and adds a reminiscence about his boyhood fights", January 20, 1901
  - New York Journal and Advertiser, New York Times -- "Mark Twain/Expert on Trade Marks/Has Fun/Says They Won't Let Me talk, He Testifies in a Suit of Rudyard Kipling's about Copyright" -- "Clemens answers some questions on copyrights as an expert, in a hearing before a United States Commissioner", March 14, 1901
  - New York World -- "Mark Twain in the Woods" -- "Clemens at Lake Saranac, refuses to be quoted on any serious subject; much description and photographs of his summer house", July 21, 1901
  - New York Journal and Advertiser -- "Mark Twain Offers to Vote for Satin", October 9, 1901
  - New York SUN, New York Journal -- "Mark Twain will Warmly Great Robbers/Riverdale Burglar-Ridden", October 11, 1901
  - New York Herald, Baltimore SUN -- "Sh-hhh Says Mark Twain", 1901-10-14 &1901-10-19
  - New York Tribune, New York SUN -- "Mark Twain Would Be a Bill Poster" -- "Actually a news story, quite possibly planted; Clemens appears at anti-Tammany headquarters and wants to go out pasting up political posters; he jeers at Tammany tactics and candidates", October 31, 1901
  - San Francisco Examiner -- "Mark Twain Says it's All Rubbish/College Education is Not Essential to the Making of a Gentleman" -- "Actually a statement or press release; Clemens rejects view that the new millionaires, if they have not been to college, can be gentlemen", March 10, 1902
  - Charleston Sunday News -- "Tom Reed and Mark Twain/Mark Twain in Town/ Mark Twain with a Julep" -- "No direct quotation but extensive summary on Mark Twain's remark: praise for Charleston Exploration", April 6, 1902
  - Saint Louis Post-Dispatch -- "Mark Twain Here as Saint Louis' Guest for the First Time Since 1861" -- "Long, loose item; Clemens comments on Bret Harte and on piloting career, recalls in detail the Punch, Brothers, Punch jingle and the heap pipe presented to him in Virginia City", May 29, 1902
  - Saint Louis Star -- "Mark Twain Laughs in Grain Pits" -- "Clemens speaks at Merchants Exchange, then chats in hotel lobby about his health and laziness and discusses river traffic with Horace Bixby", May 29, 1902
  - Saint Louis Post-Dispatch -- "Mark Twain's Visit to Hannibal" -- "Part feature story, part interview; Clemens reminisces about old friends on the river and other Missourians", May 30, 1902 - May 31, 1902
  - Saint Louis Republic -- "Mark Twain Comes Back to Missouri/Affection of Old Friends Brings Mark Twain to Tears/Reminiscences of Humorist/Mark Twain Visits His Old Sweetheart/Mark Twain Guest of President Jesse/Mark Twain's Reunion/Mark Twain at Pilot Wheel; Bids Farewell to Mississippi, May 30-31, 1902 & June 8-9, 1902
  - Saint Louis Post-Dispatch -- "Mark Twain Takes a Drive/Tom Sawyer Character in Hannibal" -- "Clemens comments to old acquaintances and reminisces casually; comments on local traditions about who were the originals for some of his characters", June 2, 1902
  - Saint Louis Post-Dispatch -- "Mark Twain Takes a Drive/Tom Sawyer Character in Hannibal" -- "Clemens comments to old acquaintances and reminisces casually; comments on local traditions about who were the originals for some of his characters", June 3, 1902
  - Hannibal Morning Journal -- "Mark Twain Going Home" -- "Mostly news story but summarizes a 30 minute conversation when the reporter found Mark Twain lying in bed puffing away on a black cigar and with a book in his hand", June 3, 1902
  - Saint Louis Star, Saint Louis Globe-Democrat -- "Mark Twain at Wheel Again" -- "Clemens chats casually about river traffic, past and present, June 6, 1902 - June 7, 1902
  - Saint Louis Post-Dispatch -- Mark Twain at Smoke Talk/Twain at Helm of Harbor Book/Mark Twain's Visit Over" -- "Clemens comments casually on events of current visit, and his taste in cigars, and he tells an anecdote about his and W.D. Howells' interest in a pretty pedestrian", June 6, 1902 - June 8, 1902
  - The Hannibal Evening Courier-Post -- "Mark Twain", June 6, 1902
  - Cassell's Magazine -- "A Day with Mark Twain" -- "Not identical with piece in New York World, 21 July 1901, but based on same visit; really a feature story with no quotations of consequence", July, 1902
  - New York World -- "My First Vacation and My Last" -- "Free ranging item; some yarn-spinning reminiscences; Clemens mentions his work on a new novel", September 7, 1902
  - New York Evening Journal -- "Mark Twain: Study of an American Who Has Interested and Amused 50,000,000 People by His Wit/Mark Twain: His Wit and Humor" -- "Reporter comes along with Homer Davenport, for a full page spread of words and pictures; Mark Twain makes some interesting comments about fossils and about Monte Carlo", December 20, 1902
  - New York World -- "Men of To-Day Who Make the World Laugh" -- "Mark Twain repudiates the interview that accompanied the Homer Davenport visit of December 1902; that is, he says he had not expected a report on the conversation to appear; refuses to be interviewed, commenting at some length on idea that writers, unlike politicians, should be paid for interviews, which use up their stock in trade", April 13, 1903
  - New York Herald -- "Mark Twain's Door Open to Burglars" -- "Frothy comment on his respect for successful burglars", June 15, 1903
  - New York Herald -- "Mark Twain on the Yacht Races" -- "Actually written by Clemens; he clowns about his knowledge of yachting and about how he has adapted his style to being paid by the word", August 30, 1903
  - New York Evening Journal -- "Mark Twain Off Shooting Shafts of Humor" -- "By far the longest of the items for this occasion; reporter picked up Mark Twain at the hotel and stayed close; Mark Twain talks about Dowie and also about Henry Lucy--OBITUARY scheme; also comments on the comparison of him to Aristophanes and Rabelais", October 24, 1903
  - New York Herald, SUN, Times, Review -- "Mark Twain Makes Some Parting Remarks/Comments on Aristophanes, Rabelais, Dowse, and Mrs. Eddy", October 25, 1903
  - Ladies Home Journal -- "Mark Twain's Pictures/Three Famous Authors" -- "Mark Twain, W.D. Howells, and Henry Van Dyke; three photos of Mark Twain with a sentence or two commentary each; two of the photos get further, quoted commentary, photos taken at Quarry Farm; not really an interview but list because of R. Willis comment"", November, 1903
  - Courier Della Sera -- "Italian Accounts of Mark Twain Aboard and at Home: An Interview and a Visit", November 12, 1903
  - Metropolitan Magazine -- "An Interview with Mark Twain" -- "Author is very obtrusive and indeed features her own opinions and anecdotes; item is finally of no consequence", March, 1904
  - The Sketch -- "Mark Twain on the Law of Copyright" -- "Clemens also comments, briefly, on Italians, Mary Baker Eddy, and mass opinion", March 30, 1904
  - New York Times -- "Mark Twain to Reform the Language of Italy" -- "A very coherent; covers Italy and Italian, Clemens's reading", April 10, 1904
  - New York Times -- "A Talk with Mark Twain's Cat/The Owner Himself Being Invisible" -- "Reporter fails to get to see Clemens", April 9, 1905
  - Boston Herald -- "The Same Old Mark Twain" -- "Long and coherent; but stresses copyright and color of Mark Twain's personality while recording same main subjects as other accounts", November 6, 1905
  - Boston Globe -- "In Genial Mood/Mark Twain Talks on Various Topics" -- "Long, coherent item; main subjects are copyright, political and business corruption in United States, Imperialism in the Congo and South Africa, and Czarist Tyranny", November 6, 1905
  - Boston Evening Transcript -- "Mark Twain Talks on 'Graft'" -- "After remarks on copyright and imperialism in South Africa, Clemens talks at length about current corruption and places its source in post-bellum speculation", November 6, 1905
  - Boston Journal -- "Mark Twain, Between Puffs, Talks Some" -- "Relaxed commentary by Clemens on copyright law, atrocities in the Congo, tyranny in czarist Russia, and the insurance scandal", November 6, 1905
  - Hartford Courant -- "Mark Twain at 70/He discusses Summer Homes and His Work" -- "Clemens wrote out the quoted parts; he details his liking for Dublin, New Hampshire, as a summer retreat and briefly mentions what pieces of writing he has worked on lately", November 25, 1905
  - New York World -- "Mark Twain on Summer Homes" -- "Quoted parts identical with Hartford Courant of 25 November and New York American and Journal of 26 November", November 26, 1905
  - New York World Sunday Magazine -- "What I am Thankful For" -- "Prearranged interview; long; dependable; Clemens discusses his dyspepsia, his habit of non-exercise, his self-editing, and (briefly) the use of humor; then launches into long, rehearsed diatribe against Leopold", November 26, 1905
  - New York Times -- "Mark Twain: A Humorist's Confession/On the Eve of His 70th Birth Anniversary, He Admits He Never Did a Day's Work" -- "Clemens discusses play v. work, his reputation and seriousness as a humorist, and national differences in humor", November 26, 1905
  - Seattle (Washington) Star -- "Samuel L. Clemens Interviews the Great Humorist, Mark Twain" -- "Clemens humorously discusses photographs and other representations of himself, wishes them to be kinder; plugs Peter Pan", November 30, 1905
  - New York Herald -- "Samuel Clemens's in Washington, D.C./Congress Admires Mark Twain's Hair", January 30, 1906
  - New York Herald -- "Mark Twain in Moving Pictures" -- "Comic photographs of Clemens with some captions presumably suggested by him", February 4, 1906
  - Hartford Courant -- "Mark Twain Pays Tribute to Servant" -- "Series of laudatory remarks about the deceased", February 28, 1906
  - New York Herald -- "Mark Twain Too Lazy for a United States Senator" -- "Clemens humorously rejects notion that he might be a senator; feels he would not be taken seriously", March 11, 1906
  - New York American and Journal -- "Huckleberry Finn's End Disappoints Mark Twain" -- "Clemens comments quizzically on the many persons over the years who have claimed to be the models for Tom and Huck", March 18, 1906
  - New York SUN, Tribune, World -- "Mark Twain on Gorky Affair/Gorky Visit/Hotels Turn Gorky Away" -- "In part or whole, probably written answers by Clemens to reporters' questions about Maxim Gorky scandal", April 15, 1906
  - New York Times and Tribune -- "Mark Twain Appeal for San Francisco/Mark Twain's Memories of the City" -- "After appeal from platform for aid to victims of San Francisco earthquake, Clemens gives reporters an anecdote about a small quake he once experienced", April 20, 1906
  - New York Evening Journal -- "Mark Twain Helps to Open the Day and Night Bank in NYC" -- "Mark Twain is among those who make deposits in the new Day and Night Bank, Mark Twain said he could deposit money there if he felt like it, but he decided not to do it for fear of exciting the envy of other authors. Mark Twain said it was a fine sign of prosperity when the town had to keep a bank going night and day", May 1, 1906
  - Human Life -- "Mark Twain Dean of Our Humorists" -- "Evidently talked with Clemens lately, when he returned for funeral of Patrick McAleer; has a few brief quoted comments; also has some local anecdotes and reminiscence of his own", May, 1906
  - Boston Sunday Post -- "Walks Around the Hudson", May 20, 1906
  - The Chattanooga Times -- "Polk Miller's Visit to Mark Twain" -- "Entertainer famous for his Old Times Down South program reports recent session of reminiscence with Clemens about antebellum and plantation days", July 7, 1906
  - New York American -- "Twain Would Like to Dress Like Adam" -- "Clemens jokes at length about men's clothing and fashions", December 8, 1906
  - New York Times -- "An Advocate of Dress Reform" -- "Clemens drolls on at length about clothing", December 8, 1906
  - Washington (D.C.) Post -- "Twain's Fancy Suit", December 8, 1906
  - Washington Evening Star, Washington Herald -- 'Mark Twain in White/Twain Awes Capitol" -- "Much joking about clothes; Clemens is sardonic about a library banning 'Eve's Diary'; brief comment on several current political matters; firm plea for renewal of copyrights", December 8, 1906
  - New York SUN, Tribune, World, Herald -- "Dress Uniform and Copyright", December 8, 1906
  - New York Times -- "Twain's Plan to Beat Copyright Law" -- "Solid interesting item, though Clemens must have stipulated there be no quoting; gives details of his intention to renew in effect the copyright of his books by adding relevant portions of autobiography to them", December 12, 1906
  - Washington (D.C.) Post -- "Heard at the Capitol" -- "Clemens offers departing judgments on how the fight for extending the term of copyright should be conducted", December 12, 1906
  - New York World -- "Mark Twain Actually in Earnest" -- "A statement obtained by Ervin Justice; Clemens feels that his white suit and his joking detracted from the serious point of his visit to Washington; argues against 42-year limit for copyright", December 16, 1906
  - New York Times -- "Twain and the Telephone" -- "Clemens praises the telharmonium and reminisces about his early use of the telephone and his habit of using profanity", December 23, 1906
  - New York American, Herald, Times, Tribune, World: Bermuda Colonist -- "New Year’s Eve Party" -- "Comments on New York State politics", January 1, 1907
  - New York Herald, New York Tribune, New York Times -- "Mark Twain Back from Bermuda", January 10, 1907
  - New York Times -- "For the Longfellow Century/Tributes to Poet by Men of Letters/Mark Twain Tells of His Visits" -- "Clemens recalls contacts with him in 1870s", February 24, 1907
  - New York Herald -- "Mark Twain Sails South" -- "Brief; Clemens gives humorous reasons for going to Bermuda", March 17, 1907
  - New York Times -- "Mark Twain's Wanderings at an End" -- "Long item; mostly history by the reporter but has some quotation; Mark Twain comments on some of his homes briefly; more unimportant, amends three or four famous anecdotes about him", March 31, 1907
  - Elmira Daily Advertiser -- "Mark Twain in Elmira" -- "Not a substantial item; Clemens resists being interviewed but finally relents to help out cub reporter; then he gives a boost to the progress for Elmira talk going around and especially to the organ manufacturing company", April 4, 1907
  - New York American -- "Mark Twain is Going to be a Buccaneer" -- "Interesting item; Mark Twain defends his plan to go down to Jamestown for a naval review, along with Rogers; comments cynically on the Peace Congress just completed at Carnegie Hall, i.e., is not very sanguine about the prospects for peace and pacifism", April 23, 1907
  - Norfolk Ledger-Dispatch -- "Marooned Mark Twain" -- "Clemens explains why he is waiting to go back to New York City alone by yacht rather than by train", May 1, 1907
  - New York American, SUN, Times, Tribune, World -- "Twain Hesitates to Admit He's Dead" -- "Clemens chaffs about report that he has been drown at sea", May 5, 1907
  - Baltimore American -- "Mark Twain at Annapolis/Mark Twain an Honored Guest" -- "Clemens chatted ten minutes between trains about recent report he had drowned, praised Southern cooking, joked about wearing ribbon of Legion of Honor", May 10, 1907
  - Baltimore News -- "Mark Twain Tells His Literary Secret and Many Other Things" -- "Fine item; long and much quotation; on his autobiography in progress; on seriousness of his work; on paying off the Webster debt; on his five works that he will leave unfinished; long attack on German, American, and British imperialism", May 10, 1907
  - Baltimore SUN -- "Mark Twain in Clover" -- "Reporters on hand at railroad station; long, useful item; mixture of superficiality and comments on purchase of Philippine Islands, the Belgian Congo, his autobiography, disfranchising the Negara, and his white suit", May 10, 1907
  - Baltimore American -- "As Mark Twain Watched the Drill" -- "Reporter followed Clemens around and got his opinions on interviewing, on his smoking, on mugwumps, and on Peace Congress; technically not an interview but worthwhile and appropriate", May 11, 1907
  - Baltimore SUN, New York Tribune -- "Mark Twain Departs/Mark Twain at Annapolis" -- "Clemens comments on his background as a journalist, how characters such as Huck and Tom are created, 'Eve's Diary', and an admitting poem about his serious side", May 12, 1907
  - New York Times -- "Mighty Mark Twain Over-Awes Marines" -- "Datelined Annapolis; probably report of a lecture; filled with familiar anecdotes", May 12, 1907
  - New York American -- "Mark Twain Tells the Secrets of Novelists" -- "Clemens contends that books and characters tend to find their own line of development once the author has conceived them and started to write", May 26, 1907
  - New York American, Times -- "Mark Twain Sails/Shiest Man Aboard/Humorist Takes His Last Trip to London from this Sphere" -- "Clemens discusses the autobiography he is writing but will hold back from publication; chats at length about his autobiography, which will create a sensation when it is eventually published after his death", June 9, 1907
  - London Evening News -- "Arrival of Mark Twain/Collecting Hints for His Funeral Procession" -- "Clemens chaffs a great deal on minor matters", June 18, 1907
  - Westminster Gazette -- "Mark Twain in London", June 18, 1907
  - London Daily Chronicle -- "Mark Twain/Mr. Clemens's Arrives in England" -- "Clemens jokes about many subjects including himself", June 19, 1907
  - London -- "G.B.S. and Mark Twain: First Greeting of Two Great Men/Mark Twain in London/Mark Twain Arrives from America/The American Humorist in London", June 18, 1907 - June 19, 1907
  - London Daily Express -- "Mark Twain in London/Wants Hints for his Funeral from Oxford Pageant/A Bright Lad" -- Interviewer lists twelve subjects that Clemens touched on and then mentions others, especially the funeral", June 19, 1907
  - London Daily Mail -- "Edgar Wallace/Mark Twain in London" -- "Attempts jocosity in Clemens's vein of humor about his funeral, his use of Italian, and his white suits", June 19, 1907
  - London Daily Mirror -- "Mark Twain Reaches England" -- "Clemens jokes about his funeral and Kipling", June 19, 1907
  - London Morning Leader -- "Mark Twain an the Secrets of Youth/In England to Receive Oxford Honor/Chaffs Interview and Himself" -- "Much joking, especially about his funeral, his ancestry, and his white suits", June 19, 1907
  - Manchester Dispatch -- "Mark Twain's Quest/Looking for Ideas for His Funerals/Meeting with G.B.S." -- "May be by W.B. Northrop; nothing unusual in the content; relative to the many other accounts of the occasion, June 19, 1907
  - New York SUN and New York Times, Chicago Inter-Ocean -- "Mark Twain Tells Sea Tales" -- "Clemens jokes in high spirits about the voyage over to England", June 19, 1907
  - New York Herald, World, Saint Louis Globe-Democrat -- "Mark Twain in London/Meets Mr. Bernard Shaw" -- "Mark Twain jokes with G.B. Shaw and winks at reporters; then comically outlines his daily routine", June 19, 1907
  - London Evening News -- "Mark Twain at Windsor/To Be One of the Guests of the King" -- "Clemens gives anecdote about the King; outlines his social schedule", June 20, 1907
  - London Daily Mail -- E.W. "Mark Twain's Plans/To Meet the King To-Morrow" -- "Summary of a drifting conversation with banquets and Clemens's funeral as the uppermost subjects", June 21, 1907
  - New York American -- "Mark Twain Again Meets His Former Chum Edward/Renew Acquaintance with the King, Which He Started Years Ago on a Bus" -- "Clemens reminisces about meeting King Edward ten years ago at Hamburg; makes statement after the garden party at Windsor", June 23, 1907
  - London -- "Mark Twain's Statement in Windsor Garden Party", June 24, 1907
  - London Evening News -- "Mark's 'Mots'/Plans and Patents a Joke for the 'Punch' Dinner" -- "No direct quotations; Clemens muses about his immediate engagements", June 24, 1907
  - London Leader -- "Mark Twain Meets King Edward/And Describes the Royal Garden Party" -- "Clemens jokes about heaven, bright clothes, napping, and his white bathrobe", June 24, 1907
  - London Daily News -- "Oxford Pageant/What Mark Twain Thought" -- "Clemens praises the pageants", June 28, 1907
  - New York Times -- "Mark Twain Living Up to His Degree/Honor Conferred upon Him/By Oxford Seems to Have Sobered Him/Is Excessively Solemn/Says England's Welcome Has Impressed Him Greatly--Calls Ceremony at Oxford Beautiful" -- "Clemens is on these good behavior", June 30, 1907
  - New York SUN -- "Mark Twain for Penny Post" -- "A long, genuine item that Clemens probably planned for; is for lower international postal rates; introduces humorous, probably fanciful autobiography about how he used to embezzle money that father gave him for stamps", July 2, 1907
  - London Daily Chronicle -- "Mark Twain/Confession Made by His Own Fireside", July 2, 1907
  - London Daily News -- "Sleepy, But Happy/Mark Twain's Regretful Farewell" -- "Mark Twain makes, July 12, 1907